我不再是 拍摄之前那个我了
I'm not the same person
that I was before the shooting.
演员
THE ACTORS
演员和记者
AND THE JOURNALIST
OF IT ALL
大演员和大记者
乡下的秋天太阴郁了
Autumn in the country
can be really muggy.
我要是这么差 那我是怎么赚到钱的
If I'm so bad, then how come
I take home the money?
他是个病态的人
He's a sick man.
- 你跟他们说得各不相同 - 我听懂了
- Have you said different things?
- I understand the question.
我与其中一个猴子确实有共鸣
I do connect
with one of the monkeys.
你今天怎么打扮这么漂亮
Why are you so dressed up today?
- 《嘉士伯酒厂》- 不 我没演过
- "Bryggeren"?
- No, I wasn't in that either.
我能问个问题吗
Can I ask you something?
我决定穿黑色 显瘦
I decided to wear black.
It makes you look thinner.
- 《斗牛士》- 不 我还没出道
- "Matador"?
- No. Before my time.
- 我首映的时候写的 - 我不记得了
- I wore it at the premiere.
- I can't remember that.
谁都可以自称演员 要是年薪百万的话
Anyone can call himself an actor
if he earns a million a year.
作者 导演 提尔 这些词联系在一起
Auteur, director, Trier...
the words are connected.
拉斯冯提尔懂得享受生活 他是个有活力有玩心的人
Lars von Trier has joie de vivre.
He's a vibrant and playful man.
这部片中 他又一次戏弄了媒介
In this movie, he plays
with the medium once again.
叫作"自动影像捕捉" 预制的画面
It's called "Automavision."
Pre-fabricated images.
全由电脑决定 提尔让机器做主了
A computer has planned it all.
Trier has let the machine decide.
极其古怪
Utterly weird.
我第一次听到时 一点都他妈没听懂
When I first heard about it
I didn't understand a damned thing.
是无穷的乐趣源泉 因为实在是太蠢了
It was a constant source of fun
because it's so stupid.
你有大堆演员
You have lots of actors,
然后摄像机选择拍一卷卫生纸
and then the camera
opts to film a kitchen roll.
我心想 "这一次他又要搞什么鬼"
I thought, "What the hell
is he up to this time?"
必须得有些约束在
There had to be some obstructions.
6分钟长的卫生纸镜头 永远没机会用
6 minutes' worth of kitchen roll
footage which will never be used.
下面这部电影 也许你已经看出有点怪异
Here's a new film.
It may look strange to you,
那么坚持住 谁都看出来了
but hang in there. There's
something for everyone, I promise.
艺术何时成为艺术
When does art become art?
何时对话心灵 何时对话头脑
When does it speak to the heart,
when does it speak to the mind?
Thes这些问题e questions are...
These questions are...
这些是你看一部提尔的新片时 需要问的问题
Those are questions you have to ask
when you see a new Trier movie.
他刚刚创作了喜剧《真假老板》
He's just made the comedy
"The Boss of It AII."
我们与演员们讨论了艺术 喜剧是轻松的 这是严肃的
We've talked to the actors about art.
Comedy is fun. This is serious.
对你而言 在与你男友共事的同时
What was it like for you
to expose yourself so much
有这么大尺度的裸露 感受如何
while also working with your
boyfriend, Casper Christensen?
有他在边上 你能适应吗
Could you cope,
with him on the sideline?
是的 我觉得能看到Casper作为一个
Yes.
I thought it was great to see
传统意义上的演员活跃起来 这样很好
how Casper came alive as an actor
in a more classical sense.
你够了吗
Are you done now?
- Iben 你的角色是主角 - 是的
- Iben, your part is a major one.
- Yes. It is.
这需要大量的准备工作
It's required
a lot of preparation work.
闭嘴 你不说我们更生气
Shut up. We'll be
more upset if you don't tell us.
- 显然也是个高难度的角色 - 是的 可以这么说
- And clearly a difficult one.
- Yes, and you could say...
她很有抱负 你知道 她真的想达到顶尖
She's ambitious, you know.
She really wants to reach the top.
来个像样的口活 不然就没得操
There'll be no banging
until you've had a good licking.
提尔把你的角色根植于你自己的生活
Trier has based your character
on your own life.
在电影中扮演你自己 是什么感受
What's it like,
playing yourself in a movie?
在电影中扮演我自己
Playing myself in a movie?
当然 我们利用自己的不同侧面 但我不是在扮演我自己
We use different sides of ourselves,
of course, but I'm not playing me.
- 概括而言 你是说 - 是的 比如说
- Overall, you mean?
- Yes, for example.
好吧
Well...
- 他很像你 不是吗 - 据提尔说 是这样的
- He resembles you, doesn't he?
- According to Trier, he does.
但我不太确定
But I'm not so sure.
他说你挺柔弱和反复无常的
He says you're quite soft
and inconsistent.
你会这样看待自己吗
Do you see yourself that way?
柔弱没有什么错 但是反复无常
There's nothing wrong
with being soft, but inconsistent...
来吧
Come on.
起来啦 来抱抱
Up you go. That's it.
Big hug.
你在台词方面帮助Casper 辅导他 我猜
You helped Casper with his lines
and coached him, I guess.
- 这对你自己的角色有帮助吗 - 没有 我得说
- Did that help your own character?
- No, I have to say...
- 我能不能 - 等一下 让我说完
- Can I...?
- Hold on. Let me finish.
- Casper得从头学起 - 不 我没有
- Casper had to start from scratch.
- No, I didn't.
是的 你有 完全是这样
Yes, you did. Completely.
说心里话 你在这种情境下就像个新生婴儿
Mentally speaking, you're like
a newborn baby in this context.
Sofie 你其中一场大戏是在动物园 猴子笼旁边
Sofie, one of your big scenes
is in the zoo, at the monkey cage.
作为演员 你是如何动用环境
What do you do as an actor
to use the environment
来塑造你的角色的
and draw on that for your part?
我和它们没什么对白 你知道
I didn't have any dialogue
with them, you know.
你觉得和那些猴子有什么共鸣吗
Did you feel any connection
with the monkey?
有点不好意思 但我不记得它们是什么了 狒狒吗
It's embarrassing, but I can't
remember what they are. Baboons?
Jens Albinus 你和提尔一起演过戏 这次怎么样呢
Jens Albinus, you've played with
Trier before. How was it this time?
这个问题我没听懂
I don't understand the question.
- 你认识他 - 我没和他一起演过戏
- You know him.
- I've never played with him.
没人告诉我你会问这个
No one has told me
you would ask about that.
我的意思是 你演过提尔的电影
What I meant was, you've
been in a Trier movie before.
噢是的 对
Oh, yes. Right...
但是这次不一样
But it was different
this time around.
- 完全不一样 - 怎么说
- It was completely different.
- In what way?
我只能说 这和某些个演员有关系
Let me just say that it has to do
with certain members of the cast.
我的经验基础相当多 你知道的
My base of experience
is enormous, as you know.
我已经开创了我自己的方法 我称之为Gantzler方法
I've created my own method...
the Gantzler Method as I call it...
因此当我接到一个新角色 我清楚地知道如何展现
so that when I get a new part
I know exactly how to approach it.
而这个家伙 Ravn 也不例外
And this guy, Ravn,
was no exception.
他叫Ravn (渡鸦) 是种鸟类 这就是突破口
He's called Ravn ("raven").
It's a bird. There's your opening.
Ravn Ravn Ravn
Ravn, Ravn, Ravn...
- 你没觉得缺乏安全感吗 - 没那么严重
- You haven't felt insecure?
- Not that much.
我没有像个白痴一样跑来跑去 说着你那些多愁善感的胡话
I don't run around like an idiot
with all your touchy-feely crap...
- 你以为你是谁 - 我在说实话
- Who do you think you are?
- I tell it like it is.
你什么都不懂 你就噼里啪啦走过来
You don't know anything.
You just come stomping in...
"我要去让拉斯冯提尔见识见识"
"I'll go in and impress
Lars von Trier..."
- 好吧 我做到了啊 - 不 你没有 你就坐在那儿
- Well, it works.
- No, it doesn't! You just sit there.
要不是我 你看着就像个呆子了
If it hadn't been for me
you would have looked like a dork.
就差这么一点了 你知道
You're this close, you know.
你能具体一点吗 你想说的是什么
Can you be more specific?
What is it you want to say?
你得小心说话
You have to watch what you say.
Peter  你对于Gantzler方法十分坦率
Peter, you're being very candid
about the Gantzler Method.
这是你和提尔一路讨论着要开发出来
Was it a technical handle
that you and Trier talked about
的技巧手法吗
developing along the way?
让我这么说吧 有一点是绝对肯定的
Let me put it this way.
I'm absolutely certain that Lars
拉斯知道我有这么一种特殊技巧
was aware that I had
this very special technique.
我们没有讨论过那么多 个人而言 我不喜欢
We didn't discuss it that much.
Personally, I don't like
让别人在我的技巧上指指点点
having people poke around
in my techniques.
但是我听其他的人说过
But I've heard
through other people
拉斯给过我很高的评价
that Lars has talked about me
in very positive terms...
不止作为个人 也是作为演员
not just as an individual,
but also as an actor.
他把这种方法说得非常有价值
He described the method
as being very valuable.
对不起 对不起
I'm sorry. I'm sorry.
要是你认为自己有半点才华  你想带着这种空洞的看法过下去
It's fine if you want to walk
through life with the hollow idea
那也没问题
that you have any talent at all.
我才不听你这种屁话 我要出去
I'm not listening to this shit.
I'd like to get out!
恐惧即诗意 诗意即恐惧 这两者在艺术的世界里
Fear is poetry, poetry is fear.
The two are closely linked
在提尔的世界里 紧密相连
in the world of art,
in the world of Trier.
许多演员将恐惧作为一种驱力
Many actors use fear
as a driving force.
所以你可以问 "恐惧是否一种驱力"
So you could ask,
"Is fear a driving force?"
Louise 你在拍摄过程中害怕吗
Louise, were you afraid
during the filming?
- 是的 她害怕 - 一点点
Yes, she was. A bit.
- 什么 - 你为什么要那么说
- What?
- Why do you say that?
作为演员 你总是在害怕做得不够好
As an actor, you're always afraid
of not being good enough.
不被人喜欢 这就是你为什么会做这个 你知道
And not being loved.
That's why we do it, you know.
- 你也害怕吗 - 是的
- Were you afraid as well?
- Yes.
是的 她害怕
Yes. She was.
你总是在开玩笑 有时候让我困惑
You joke a lot. Sometimes
I don't know exactly what to think.
分不清你是不是在开玩笑 我没法回复
I can't respond when I don't
know if it was a joke or not.
你有过和猴子合作的经验吗
Do you have any experience
in working with monkeys?
是的 我有 我以前试过
Yes, I have.
I've tried it before.
在这种情况下 你有什么要求要提吗
Do you make any demands
in that sort of situation:
"这一次我不想碰猴子了"
"This time I don't want
to touch the monkey"?
没有 你是想说 这次我是否想要不同的动物吗
No. Did I want different animals
this time, you mean?
是的 或者和猴子的接触 很简单
Yes, or contact with the monkeys,
quite simply.
- 什么 - 你不想要这种接触
- Sorry?
- That you didn't want that.
不 不能这么说 他选择猴子是有原因的
No, I can't say that. There's
a reason why he chose monkeys.
如果这样对这场戏最好 那我没问题
If that's what's best for the scene,
then I'm ready to do it.
这整个演艺行业都空洞得不可思议
The whole acting business
is incredibly hollow.
这不是种你能学会的东西 你要么行 要么不行
It's not something you can learn.
You either have it, or you don't.
我认为Iben行 她很有才华
I think Iben's got it.
She's really talented.
但她年纪大了 所以她不能挑挑拣拣
But she's getting older,
so she can't pick and choose.
时机不是种你能在学校学会的东西
Timing isn't something
you can learn in a school.
所以他们国家电影学院那些屁话
So all their National School
of Theatre crap...
跑来跑去 什么"你能感受到这些沙子吗"
running around, going
"Can you feel the sand?"
而那里根本没什么该死的沙子 你是想唬弄谁
when there isn't any goddamn sand.
Who are you trying to fool?
我做演员已经16年了 演过15-20部电影
I've been an actor for 16 years.
I've been in 15-20 films.
- 我在想《瓦尔特与卡洛》- 不 那不是我
- I'm thinking "Walter and Carlo"?
- No, that wasn't me.
你知道我的名字吗
Do you even know my name?
我有一种罕见的能力 仅凭想着什么东西
I've got the rare ability
to influence people around me
就能影响我身边的人
just by thinking certain things.
因此 如果我看到一个演员不太行
Therefore, if I see an actor
who hasn't quite got it,
我可以通过意念传送点导演诀窍给拉斯
I can mentally transfer
direction tips to Lars,
他就可以传达过去 通常都很成功
which he can then pass on.
Usually with great success.
Peter Gantzler是一个病得非常非常重的人 非常非常重
Peter Gantzler is
a very, very sick man.
- 你是什么意思- 还是不要说了
- What do you mean by that?
- Let's not get into that.
Peter Gantzler 一个病人 他只是个演员 不是吗
Peter Gantzler, a sick man?
He's just an actor, isn't he?
我才是导演 你只是演员
It's a good thing that I'm
the director, and you're just an actor.
我嗅到你的恐惧背后有故事 是什么故事
I sense a story behind your fear.
What is that story about?
这
It...
我还是不要了说 不要说
I'd rather not talk about it.
Don't say anything.
哇
Gosh...
你一定害怕自动影像捕捉来着吧
You must have been
afraid of Automavision?
其实我们发明了一种叫作"自动表演"的
We've actually invented this thing
called "Automa-action."
非常类似 当你提出一个问题
It's very similar.
When you pose a question,
你以为会得到相应的答案 但其实不会
you think you're getting the
corresponding answer, but you're not.
作为演员 恐惧是你必备的工具之一吗 这样说
As an actor, does fear have to be
part of your toolbox, so to say?
不 我想不是 我想
No, I don't think so.
I think...
好吧 食堂吃的还挺多种多样 你不觉得吗
Well... the canteen food
was quite varied, don't you think?
就是 就是一天中的高潮 你知道
It was... It was the highlight
of the day, you know?
不论你是否得到了满足
Whether or not
you got any satisfaction...
食物方面
foodwise.
重点在于你是否有计划 就是这个
It's about whether or not
you project. That's the thing.
要是你浪费了4年 到处鬼混 喝喝啤酒
If you've wasted four years,
fucking around, drinking beer,
穿什么颜色的拖鞋跳跳舞 难怪你这么刻薄
trying to dance a certain color
in slippers... no wonder you're bitter.
看到其他人高中毕业也混得不错的时候 你知道
When the rest of us can get by
just with high school, you know.
你演过什么电影
Which films have you been in?
太多了 我没法全记住
There are so many.
I can't remember them all.
有… 我也拒绝过一大堆
There's been... I've said no
to a lot of things as well.
你害怕的是提尔吗
Is it Trier you're afraid of?
哪方面让你觉得提尔是一个作者导演
In what way do you feel
that Trier is an auteur?
问我点别的
Ask me about something else.
提尔打来电话的时候 你是不是想 "提尔 就是说奖项"
When Trier calls you do you think,
"Trier... that means awards"?
- "这能让我再拿个奖" - 是的
- "This will get me another award"?
- Yes.
要是我们谈票房和评分
If we talk ticket sales
or ratings
或者周刊杂志上的"年度电视"
or "TV Host of The Year"
in the weekly magazines...
我不知道你是否想谈那些 但要是你想
I don't know if you want to go
there, but if you do...
那么是的 我们都拿过奖
then yes, we've all won awards.
你留意到我们拍完这部片后 西兰岛北部
Have you noticed the drastic change
in the North Zealand weather
剧烈的天气变化了吗
after we shot this movie?
- 什么 - 我住在北部那边
- What?
- I live in the northern part.
我花园里的天气 再也不一样了
The weather in my garden
hasn't been the same since.
- 这和Gantzler有什么关系 - 问他去啊
- What's it got to do with Gantzler?
- Well, ask him that.
所有演员并不都是同等地敏锐 你知道
Not all actors are equally
responsive, you know.
而这部片的选角
And the casting on this film...
我没时间给拉斯具体的指示
I didn't have time to give Lars
specific instructions about
关于各个角色我想选谁
who I would like to see
in the various parts,
所以他选出来的就有点 不全可靠
so his choices are a bit...
shaky in places.
但是 人都会犯错
But... to err is human.
但这很困难 尤其是
But it was difficult,
especially with...
Jens那边
with Jens.
I've got this spot between
the second and third vertebrae
which hasn't been the same since.
And every time I hear his name
it gets worse.
God, I'm furious!
Ravn is the key character,
so it's important to me
that Jens respects the fact that
I'm the star, and follows my lead.
That was hard for him.
He clearly has no method whatsoever.
He's out of a very different,
more clownlike tradition, perhaps.
It's terribly difficult
to work with sometimes.
You're just acting scared now.
Yeah, that's right. I am.
We're just acting.
That's an actor's specialty.
- Were you in "The Idiots"?
- Yes, I was, actually.
- Have you seen it?
- I've seen some clips.
- We don't see all the films.
- No, of course. There are so many.
Of course I do. Thank you.
Do you go for both the Bodil and
Robert Awards when you choose a part?
No. I go for
the Bodil Award, primarily.
- How believable was that line?
- Not bad.
The Robert Awards are a bit
more unpredictable, to be honest.
They're harder to plan for.
It seems very random.
You can look at something
and say, "This is Bodil material"?
Yes.
Didn't you feel
like an outsider sometimes?
Yes. I can't be so narcissistic,
stare at myself in the mirror
and do my hair for hours
like Peter Gantzler did.
But I've had other experiences
that they haven't had
because they were up in some loft,
doing improvisations.
The rest of us were out there
doing stand-up and making big money.
We're talking free drinks,
full throttle,
chicks and the rest of it.
That's what makes a man.
You can't ask more of a man than
what he can give. In that way...
I felt sorry for Jens.
He clearly wasn't up to the job.
And it's true that I taunted him
sometimes. Put him in his place.
Would you feel better if we didn't
talk about Peter Gantzler at all?
- That's probably the best thing.
- Jens, this movie...
No, stop it.
I can't do it anymore.
Trier's movies are very arty-farty,
I guess.
But Trier is an extremely
insecure man.
When he meets someone like me
who isn't, he attaches himself to me.
He calls me and says,
"What do I do? I don't want to fly."
I tell him,
"Goddamn it, Trier. Drive!"
You don't get that look from the
others, "She's won a lot of awards"?
- You'll have to ask them.
- You don't feel it?
I think I choose to shut it out.
Hasn't Trier won more awards
than me? He must have.
I wouldn't say I'm his mentor
or coach. I'm more a kind of rock
on which he can place
his film genius, perhaps.
- You bring Trier into a new era?
- No, he does that himself.
But we all know that if Iron Maiden
play a concert in Edinburgh...
they do the performing,
but how did they get there?
With your enormous
mental resources...
- I think it's safe to say that?
- Yes.
The resources that you have,
in this situation as well...
Right now? Yes.
If you were to draw on that to give
Lars von Trier some advice
to take with him
on his journey,
what would it be?
"When you can't be like me, Lars,
just be yourself."
Yes.
What's been
your best advice to him?
It must have been...
"Deep breaths, Lars.
Just get going.
Forget about doing
new things all the time.
Drop it. Let's have some fun."
When people look back at my films
in a hundred years' time,
they'll probably say, "Bloody hell!
That guy knew what he was doing."
I'll just go and check
that Iben is okay.
She's got the car keys, so...
- Don't you have any more questions?
- Yes.
We're just acting, aren't we?
- Are you acting?
- Yes. Couldn't you tell?
- No.
- Great acting. I really tried.
You've experienced it for yourself.
The insight into the world of art.
Powerlessness, power.
Joy, enthusiasm, feelings... fear.
Reality, parallel reality...
Thank you for watching.
When you turn up in the morning,
ready to shoot some scene...
it's like entering...
- different rooms.
- What rooms?
And one of those rooms
that you're constantly in
is the room filled with fear,
I guess.
If you don't want to do
the interview that we agreed on,
you can say whatever
you want. I'm leaving!
That's okay.
You can't help laughing
when you're fearful.
That's perfect. Brilliant.
Cut!
Why does he ask me that?
There was a bit more nonsense
in this one.
- I'm so involved with my work.
- That's good.
- "Pip."
He's fabulous.
Let me just have a look.
- And this one is all of the text?
- Yes, it's those two.
I'll get these onto some cardboard.
"And even though I may seem
like a reflection, this film is not."
I'm happy with it.
That's a punch right in their faces.
Put it there,
and I'll go up and have a look.
Put one here by my finger.
- That's nothing.
- There you go.
I'd like a movement going
diagonally across the windows.
This is some toy.
If this looks odd already, please stay,
because it won't be difficult.
- That's good.
- It's super! That's it.
- 13 degrees to the left.
- That won't work.
- It's the wrong direction.
- Let's have a new one.
Tilt down 11 degrees.
And 33 centimeters to the left.
You'll like this, Lars.
Well, if you're happy, I'm happy.